U.S. Emergency Board No. 81 Records 5037
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Emergency Board No. 81 Records
1950
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Emergency Board
5037
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Consist of carrier and employee exhibits; awards, reports, etc.; also documents pertaining to the General Rules Movement.
8855905
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, August 21, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 04, 2019
Biographical / Historical
An Executive order of the President dated February 24, 1950 resulted in the appointment of a board composed of Hon. Roger I. McDonough, justice, Supreme Court of Utah, Chairman, Hon. Mart J. O'Malley former justice, Supreme Court of Indiana; and Professor Gordon S. Watkins, University of California. Public hearings were held in Chicago, Illinois, beginning March 2, 1950, through May 9, 1950 the record consisting of 49 volumes of 8,385 pages, and 143 exhibits.
Upon stipulation of the parties and approval of the President, two extensions of time were granted, allowing to June 15, 1950, for rendition of the Board's report to the President.
The emergency precipitating the establishment of this- board resulted from the announced intention of the employees represented by the two organizations, to withdraw from the service of the railroads represented by the Carriers' Conference Committees, in connection with their demands for proposed new rules and changes in existing rules governing working conditions affecting primarily conductors, trainmen, yard service employees, and certain dining car and other groups of employees, altogether about 180,000 employees of the nation's major railroads.
The issues were numerous and complex, involving such matters as the 40-hour workweek; differentials for car retarder operators, footboard yardmasters, and baggage-men handling United States mail; graduated rate of pay tables in all classes of service; the restoration of the standard wage rates between territories; and modification of other rules. Also involved were carriers' proposals to change pay provisions, rules, regulations, interpretations, and practices pertaining to the 40-hour workweek (if recommended) interdivisional, and intradivisional runs; pooling of cabooses; switching limits; and numerous other proposals.
On June 15, 1950, the board made its report to the President, recommending a 5-day, 40-hour basic workweek for railroad yard service employees, with an increase in basic rates of pay of 18 cents per hour, effective October 1, 1950. Upward adjustments in rates of pay for car retarder operators, footboard yardmasters and baggagemen handling United States mail were also recommended. The board recommended the withdrawal of a number of other proposals of the organizations, including one which called for a graduated basis of pay for road conductors and trainmen. The board also recommended against the establishment of a 100-mile, 5-hour basic day in passenger service to replace the 150-mile, 7 1/2-hour basic day. Among the changes in rules proposed by the railroads, the board recommended that the carriers and the organizations negotiate revisions in rules to permit interdivisional runs, pooling of cabooses, and changes in yard switching limits; redefinition of rules covering coupling and uncoupling air hoses; inclusion of a rule covering rate of pay for work performed in more than one class of service in a tour of duty, and change in reporting for duty rules. It recommended the withdrawal of other carrier proposed rules changes.
During the course of the hearings in this case, two additional disputes on similar issues were referred to this same board by the President. (See Emergency Boards Nos. 83 and 84).
Scope and Contents
Consist of carrier and employee exhibits; awards, reports, etc.; also documents pertaining to the General Rules Movement.
Records include carrier exhibits dealing with work rules, wage rates and differentials, hours of work, the history of the diesel rules movement, and working conditions. Employee exhibits include statistics on then existing economic conditions in the U.S., hours and wages in other industries, productivity comparisons, and studies of the impact of dieselization on the industry and the workforce and studies of safety matters. Also miscellaneous documents of unknown origin relating to the questions considered by this Board.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States -- Cases; Wages and labor productivity -- United States; Railroad conductors; Railroads -- Employees; Hours of labor -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Industrial safety -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Labor productivity -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- Railroads -- United States; Railroads -- Safety regulations -- United States; Railroads -- Dieselization -- United States; Wages -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Wages -- Railroads -- United States; Work rules -- Railroads -- United States; Working conditions -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; Eastern Carriers' Conference Committee; Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen; Order of Railway Conductors of America; Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committee; United States. Emergency Board No. 81; Western Carriers' Conference Committee
8855905
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit B, History of the General Rules Movement Involving the Class I Rail carriers and Their Engine, Train, and Yard Service Employees, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit C, Statutes, Awards and Agreements Involved in the Great Rules Movements, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules case, Carriers' Exhibit D, Misc. Reports, Awards, Agreements, and Interpretations Involving Wages and Working Conditions of Railroad Employees, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 19, L. W. Horning, Basic Day and Overtime Rule in Passenger Service, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 16, Use of Road Crews to Perform Work in Yard, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 4, History of The Diesel Rules Movement, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Conductor's and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit E, 40-Hour Work Week for Railroad Employees and for Railway Express Agency Employees, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Emergency Board No. 81, Case A-3290, Carriers Represented by Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committees and Order of Railway Conductors Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit A, The Proposals of the Parties and The Issues Before the Board, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Conductors' and trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit No. 5, Witness: GP Brock, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit No. 3, Witness: JM Budd, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit No. 2, Witness: JM Symes, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Conductors' and trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 15, Use of Trainmen and Yardmen to Couple and Uncouple Hose, Chain and Unchain Cars and Make Air Tests, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 14, Rate of Pay for Footboard Yardmaster, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Conductor's and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 13, Rate of Pay for Car Retarder Operators, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 12, Penalty Pay for Work on Sundays and Holidays in Yard Service, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Conductors and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 11, Starting Time for Yard Crews, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit, 10-a, Witness: DP Loomis, Appendices Referred to in Carriers Exhibit Entitled 48 Hours Pay for 40 Hours of Work, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Conductors' and Trainmen 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit, DP Loomis, 48 Hours Pay for 40 Hours of Work, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 9, Witness: DP Loomis, Rates of Pay for Yard Service Employees, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Conductor's and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 8, Duties of Firemen on Diesel Locomotives, Employees' Exhibit No. 66, Firemen's Diesel Case, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Conductor's and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carrier's Exhibit 7 Duties of Enginemen in Diesel Engine Rooms, Employees Exhibit No. 17, Engineers' Diesel Case, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Conductor's and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 6, Duties of Engineer and Assistant on Diesel Locomotives, Employees' Exhibit No. 15, Engineers' Diesel Case, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 38, Financial Condition of the Railroads, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 38, Witness: J. Elmer Monroe, Financial Condition of the Railroads, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Conductors' and trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit no. 35, Safety, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit No. 31, LD Comer, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 30, Witness: LD Comer, Right of Management to Fix the Time of Reporting For Road Crews, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 29, Additional pay for Initial Terminal, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Conductors' and trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules case, Carriers' Exhibit 28, Witness: LD Comer, Pay For Expenses Away From Home, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit No. 23, Witness: DC Raffensparger, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Conductors' and trainmen's 40-Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 20, Witness: LW Horning, Overtime Rate in Passenger Service, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Conductors' and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit 18, Witness: JJ Sullivan, Road Employees Performing More Than One Class of Road Service, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Emergency Board No. 81, Case A-3290, Carriers Represented by Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committees and Order of Railway Conductors, Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Brief on Behalf of the Carriers, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Conductors and Trainmen's 40 Hour Week and Rules Case, Carriers' Exhibit No. 1, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Index to Opening Case of Order of Railway Conductors and Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Employees' Exhibit Nos. 1-7, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Employees Exhibits Nos. 8-12 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Employees Exhibits Nos. 13-19 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Employees Exhibits Nos. 20-25 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Employees Exhibit Nos. 26-30 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Employees Exhibits Nos. 30-40 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Employees Exhibits Nos. 41-48, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Employees Exhibits Nos. 49-55 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Index to Carriers' Case Employees' Rebuttal and Closing Arguments, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Employees' Rebuttal Exhibit Nos. 57-62, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Employees' Rebuttal Exhibit Nos. 63-69, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Employees' Exhibit Nos. 76-86 (Box 2, Folder 13)